<title>Establishment of a Causal Relation</title>

The nature of an effect and a cause is established even by threefold cognition consisting of perception and non-perception; some others, however, demand five. (v.1.)

It is a rule that a causal relation is proved by perception and non-perception. Concerning this rule, some say that what proves it is threefold cognition, i.e. either two successive perceptions (Nos. 2 & 3) which respectively have (a cause and an effect) as their object and which are accompanied by a prior non-perception (No. 1) grasping both (of the objects) jointly, or two successive non-perceptions (Nos. 4 & 5) accompanied by a (prior) perception grasping both (of the objects) jointly (No. 2-3). The others, however, demand five cognitions which occur in a definite order of succession, i.e. the three (of the first group) together with the last two (non-perceptions). (They argue:) Because even if the first three are available, the cognizer does not acquire doubtless knowledge, while he obtains it when he has experienced the last two as well, for a causal relation is characterized by (two aspects, viz.,) the concomitance in agreement (<i>anvaya<\i>) and the concomitance in difference (<i>vyatireka<\i>). Of these, the <i>anvaya<\i> is known by the (first) three cognitions and the <i>vyatireka<\i> by the (last) two. Thus we establish (a causal relation) successfully by means of fivefold cognition.

It is examined in the following:

If the prior non-perception does not negate (the three modes of presence) such as 'coming from another place', what is its use? If it negates, what is the use of the last? (v. 2.)

(The last means the last) twofold non-perception. Non-perception is requested in order to prove a <i>vyatireka<\i>, and this can be proved by the (non-perception) sublating the presence of a supposed effect when the supposed cause is absent. And presence is possibly of three kinds: continued presence on a spot, coming from another place, and birth from a separated aggregate.<footnote>For the theory of the three kinds of presence see also Hetubinduṭīkā (GOS ed.) 45, 18-21; Śākyamati (A. 5.)</footnote>

If the sublation of these kinds is not made, why is that (non-perception) expected?<footnote>Read "<i>ayam apekṣyate<\i>".</footnote>

(The <i>pañcakavādin<\i>:) "It (i.e. the first non-perception) is of no use for (the determination) of a <i>vyatireka<\i>,<footnote>Bring "na vyatireke' syôpayogaḥ" to the top of the next line.</footnote> but we see that it renders some assistance to the perception which grasps an <i>anvaya<\i>."

<page>Page 6</page>

When this is, that occurs: Is this not understood by sense perception? (v. 3a-b.)

For anvaya means no other than the presence (of a thing) due to the presence (of another). This is established by perception. What is then the use of the assistance of non-perception? (The pañcakavādin:) “If so, even a thing which by accident approaches (an effect) may be admitted to be necessarily concomitant, for, even then, the mere perception (of the two) is possible.” (The author:) Such an over-reasoning (atiprasaṅga) is out of question because we say that the perception which grasps it (anvaya) is qualified by (a non-perception) grasping the prior absence. Again, this prior absence, which is by nature contrary to the presence divided into the (above-said) three kinds, is either established by non-perception or is merely a constant absence (abhāvamātra).<footnote>Omit two commas in 318, 4.</footnote> If the first alternative is maintained, it follows: When this is present, that occurs,

Since it is not born otherwise; this means none other than the vyatireka (v. 3 c-d.) It has not been present there, nor born from another thing, nor has come from another place; if this is present the effect is produced, if this is not, no effect is produced. (v. 4.)

And this much is proved by the perception preceded by non-perception, and accordingly there is no use of the last two. What proves the vyatireka is (a non-perception which) sublates the continuous presence on the spot (of an effect), its birth from another thing and its arrival from another place<footnote></footnote> due to the effort of others, but truly not the last two, because even a hundred of non-perceptions are inefficient if they do not have the (sublating) function<footnote></footnote>: Since this proof (of a vyatireka) is given by the first one (non-perception), the others are useless.

However (the <i>pañcakavādin</i>, resorting to the second alternative) may think that the prior non-perception is a cognition of a mere constant absence. (But this is untenable.)

If the prior non-perception is a cognition of a constant absence, it is still of no use. If it is known that the (effect) is (absent) before the function (of its cause), then what is left? (v. 5.)

First, when a constant absence is known, the question remains: what is con-

FN: Tibetan version (Peking ed., Ze, 400, a 1: <i>gźan nas 'oṅs pa<\i>) supports the reading "<i>anyata āgamanam<\i>".

FN: Read "<i>vyāpāra<\i>".

<page>Page 7</page>

comitant with what? Besides, even the knowledge of an anvaya that when C is, E occurs cannot<footnote></footnote> prevent the application of an over-reasoning of an (unrelated) object which has by accident come near. And if (on the contrary) it is known that E is absent before the operation of C, then it is tantamount to the knowledge understood by threefold cognition. What then is left for which the last two could be considered useful?

If (you want to say that) since there is a possibility of deviation even when an anvaya alone is perceived the vyatireka is sought after, why do you not say it when perceptions alone are operating? (v. 6.)

(This is the very reason) why we seek for the prior (non-perception). The anvaya and the vyatireka combined together mean causal relation, though they, if taken severally, may deviate from it. The rule that though one of them alone is not of the nature (of causality), they, if co-present, are not sublated holds good for us too. Thus, it has been established that the first is of no use for the last two and these are of no use for the first.

(The <i>pañcakavādin</i>:) “It has not been established, for even if we know by the first cognition that E was not present before the operation of C, it is not yet ascertained that the absence of E is necessarily connected with the absence of the operation of C. And this is indeed ascertained by the last two.” (The author:) This is not correct, because the uselessness of the first cognition remains as before. Again:

We determine (a vyatireka) by the last (two non-perceptions) because the absence (of an effect is derived) from the absence of its (cause) alone. Why is it not understood by the prior (non-perception), when the same logic can be applied to it. (v. 7.)

(The knowledge that E was) not present before the operation of C makes known the absence (of an effect) derived from the absence of its cause, for it is concluded through excluding the above-said three kinds of existence. Therefore, if the (first cognition) cannot ascertain (a vyatireka), let the last two be inefficient as well. How can you then attach much faith only to the last two, while thinking that you do not know by the first cognition the necessary connection of one thing with the other, but (do know) the mere (accidental) co-presence of two things. When one of the two things would occur independently without the other, the second absence (i.e. the posterior non-perception) would be equally inapplicable to it. It may be said that when smoke is produced just

FN: I propose to read "<i>apari-panthini<\i>" instead of "<i>paripanthini<\i>".

<page>Page 8</page>

after an ass and fire have appeared together, the first non-perception may tell us of the absence of the smoke at the time of the absence of the ass. But the last two cognitions may also (suggest the same wrong conclusion) when (smoke) is absent after both (the ass and the fire) are gone. And if you pursue a series of means one after another, then you will lose the fixed limit of five. You may point out that we have thus counted not two, but three (last non-perceptions of which the objects are fire, ass and smoke). But our intention is to explain that the last two cognitions are as well inefficient; there is no use of counting two or three.<footnote></footnote> If you insist that the two non-perceptions and also the other (i.e. the first) are useful, since (the vyatireka) is not determined when they are not available, we should say, since the non-perception (of an effect) at the time of the absence of the cause alone is in question, why do you not admit that the first cognition is efficient too. If you do not admit this, it would follow, as is already said, that every (non-perception) is useless. Or otherwise we can say that even the number of perception must be three, but not two. To the pañcakavādin who is not different from us in following the same doctrine (of Dharmakīrti), one prior non-perception is permitted. This one non-perception must be counted when the fire and the ass have gone away, and if you add the succeeding non-perception of the smoke, you get two this time too (i.e. at the end of the series of cognitions). Again:

Perceiving successively the (two things) which were not seen before, or perceiving successively the disappearance of the two things which were seen before, we come to know the definite relation of a cause and an effect; otherwise, it would require an infinite series (of cognitions) (v. 8.) because an infinite series of perceptions and non-perceptions would be sought after at the beginning as well as at the end in order to remove doubts which take place one after another. Therefore, in any case, the number must be limited to three or some other according to our wish. However, the two non-perceptions before and after the perception, which is placed in the middle, have no use at all, because if either of them is suspected, both of them would be doubted<footnote></footnote> and when we have scrutinized them, we come to know that one of them is enough to establish (a vyatireka). Therefore:

When an anvaya and a vyatireka have been determined through perception and non-perception, what kind of doubt is there in the establishment of a

FN: Read "<i>sa tu dvayas trayo veti....<\i>"

FN: Read "<i>anāśvāsāt<\i>".

<page>Page 9</page>

causal relation? (v. 9.)

Though different in form, both (<i>anvaya<\i> and <i>vyatireka<\i>) have one and the same nature of causality. There is no definite order<footnote></footnote> of comprehending the two; two different orders are admitted.

(The <i>pañcakavādin<\i>) may contend : "The determination (of causality) is made due to the steadfastness of a <i>vyatireka<\i>. Therefore, it is proper that non-perception grasping a <i>vyatireka<\i> surpasses (in frequency) perception of which the object is an <i>anvaya<\i>." (The author :) No. It is not the frequency, but the logical necessity of an instrument of knowledge which bestows firmness to its object, for mere frequency is experienced in the case of a fallacious proof too. Non-perception of what is by nature perceptible, even if it occurs only once, is absolutely fit to prove the absence when the thing is absent ; what is the use of chasing after frequency? For when (the absence is confirmed by it) there wouldn't even be the smell of smoke. (The <i>pañcakavādin<\i> :) "It is certainly due to repeated absence that we are able to determine what is the thing owing to the absence of which smoke is not produced." (The author :) For that very (determination), we expect a perception grasping an <i>anvaya<\i> when the absence of one thing has been connected with the absence of another, which would not (then) appreciate the meeting of (another) absence. In the same way, when the determination is made by making the perception grasping an <i>anvaya<\i> prior, we see the co-presence of many things and accordingly want to know the thing due to the presence of which this (smoke) is present ; then, through non-perception we know that the absence of this is now connected with the absence of that ; and we conclude that the presence of this was connected with the presence of that previously too. In this case, knowledge can be when we have made each of the positive and negative application once. Such being the case, it has been proven that either the prior or the posterior (non-perception) alone is able to establish a <i>vyatireka<\i> and that if you (rely on) applying a number, even the twofold (number) is inefficient.

Besides, this determination by fivefold cognition is not pervasive,<footnote></footnote> for we can establish (a causal relation) even in the cases of fire and ash, a jug and a potter etc. where the posterior (non-perception) is not available and in the cases of water and a receptacle etc. where the prior (non-perception) is unavailable. For if a man who has perceived that the water (in a pond) rested full when the bank

---

FN: Read "<i>na pratīti-krama-niyamaḥ<\i>" according to T (Ze, 401, a 4: rtogs pa'i rim pa ṅes pa med pas....)

FN: I. e. not universally applicable.


<page>Page 10</page>

was (in a satisfactory condition) sees later that it is not so when the bank is not<footnote></footnote> (satisfactory), the determination of the causal relation between the two things is made without depending upon the prior (non-perception). In the other case too, it should be known, only three cognitions are required.

(The pañcakavādin:) “If a man who, not having a prior experience, sees smoke in the vicinity of fire, can he not think that some other thing produces smoke with the help of fire? In this case too, fire actually has as much causeness as fuel. Let him then think that another thing, say an ass, which has by accident approached there, is a cause. It would follow that he would infer the presence of an ass from smoke.” (The author:) Do you mean (by this simile) that an ass is as well a cause (of smoke) because fire is definitely a cause or because both perception and non-perception are functioning there? But (you cannot say so) as they are both incorrect. Besides, we resort to the three cognitions not in order to deny that something other (than fire) is a cause as well, but to affirm that fire is. Since this is proven, the non-denial of others does not annul it. But a false inference (such as that of an ass from smoke) takes place only because the causal relation is not (there) determined. That an ass may sometimes make (smoke) with the help of fire is merely a supposition and not determined knowledge, because, being by nature a doubt, it is contrary<footnote></footnote> (to determined knowledge). Even such (an idea) can be denied only through the examination of that (causality), and not otherwise. Therefore this kind of incoherent argument is irrelevant.

(The <i>pañcakavādin<\i>:) “However, the rule is unstable as the restriction of the cause to fire is inapplicable. Fire is not the only cause, because other causes are not excluded, and fuel is also a cause in reality. (Again, fire is not necessarily) the cause (of smoke) because there is possibly a fire making no smoke.” (The author:) This should not be contended, for three kinds of exclusion or separation (vyavaccheda) are established.<footnote></footnote> That is:

When a totality is concerned the others are excluded; when a substance in relation to (a certain) fitness is concerned the non-connection is severed; regarding an action the absolute non-connection is severed. (v. 10.)

When by the word ‘fire’ we mean as a whole the entire things (fire, fuel, mois-

FN: The original Mss. (<i>tadabhāve tadabhāva\i>) is right. Tibetan translation is misleading here.

FN: T "<i>niścayavirodhāt<\i>". But I followed Skt.

FN: I will give a detailed discussion on the three kinds of <i>vyavaccheda<\i> at the earliest possible opportunity. See Additional note too.

<page>Page 11</page>

ture etc.) implied by it, that much alone is (the cause of smoke) (<i>sa eva kāraṇam<\i>) and here the connection of the others is severed (<i>anyayogavyavaccheda<\i>).

When only the substance of fire is meant and also when cause-ness means fitness (or latent force), then (fire) is fit to be (one of) the causes (of smoke) (<i>dahanaḥ kāraṇam eva<\i>). This is the separation of the non-connection (<i>ayogavyavaccheda<\i>).

When furthermore an actual action<footnote></footnote> is meant, (it means that fire) actually can be (a cause) (<i>dahanaḥ kāraṇam bhavaty eva<\i>). Here the separation of the absolute non-connection (<i>atyantāyogavyavaccheda<\i>) is admitted. And since this much of function can be made by the aforesaid three positive and negative perceptions, the very interpretation of the revered master Arcaṭa concerning this section is correct. The blessed author of the (<i>Pramāṇa<\i>-)<i>vārttika<\i> himself

Means the same when he says: A pot is made by a potter, ash by fire and a wound by a sword etc. etc. (v. 11.)

(The <i>pañcakavādin<\i>:) “Why can we not infer fire from ash just as from smoke when these two are the same in so far as they are effects?” “Never, because (inferring) is permitted in relation to a particular place, time etc. That is:

Some effects depend on the cause only for their origination, while others also for the continuation of their stream; in this respect (the effect) is time-bound. (v. 12.)

Among them, (if one infers) from those effects such as a jug, ash etc. which depend on others only for their origination, i.e. from those which depend on another thing for the cessation of their stream, the only time of which one can make a conclusion as to the co-presence of a cause is a past time, and not the present. Thus, here a mixed-presence of the activity etc. (of the cause with the effect) cannot be. From the latter (effects) such as smoke, light etc. which depend on a particular state, but not (on other things) for the cessation of their stream, i.e. from those which do not expect others for the cessation of their stream because it occurs by the deficiency in the material cause, only the present time can be inferred. Therefore, there is no error (named above). In respect to the (latter effects), Ācārya Dharmottara’s effort to resort to the last two cognitions may be fruitful, but even then the determination of five cannot be meritorious. The former (theory, i.e. the <i>trikavāda<\i>) is superior because in the case of non-perception accompanied by prior perception, there is no need of depending on the other (i.e. the first non perception).

---

FN: T ze, 402, a7: don bya ba=<i>arthakriyā<\i>.